<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Fix It In Firmware</title><link>https://fixitinfirmware.com/</link><description>A site dedicated to care and feeding of embedded systems</description><atom:link href="https://fixitinfirmware.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:rhempel@fixitinfirmware.com"&gt;Ralph Hempel&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 14:55:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Let's Be Innovative!</title><link>https://fixitinfirmware.com/posts/lets-be-innovative/</link><dc:creator>Ralph Hempel</dc:creator><description>&lt;img alt="Lunar Lander Research Vehicle Pilot - Kluever" class="align-right" src="https://fixitinfirmware.com/images/accent/LLRV-pilot-kluever.thumbnail.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your department has undergone another re-organization because ... actually
it doesn't matter. One of the reasons for the change was to step-change
the innovation culture so that your company can quickly deliver world-class
experiences that delight your customers and exceed their expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sound familiar? Depressingly familiar? Wasn't this supposed to be one
of the outcomes of the last reorganization? What happened?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, take heart. Leadership doesn't wake up one morning and decide
on how to make things worse. There is a genuine desire to
make things better - what's missing sometimes is asking the right questions
that drive change in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's have a look at why innovation is so hard to achieve in some
business environments, and what we can do to turn things around. This
is definitely not a list of "5 Easy Ways To Innovate" - it's more
about taking stock of where your organization is today, and deciding on
the first steps towards where you want it to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="what-is-innovation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Innovation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to think about innovation is the combination of two or
more well known ideas into something new. Notice that I used
ideas - not technologies, or applications, or processes, or even
customer requests. An idea can be any of these things and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innovation is hybrid of research and development. It's a
place where you need to be able to test if two or more ideas can
be combined (research) and then convert that into a product or a
component that can be used in a product (development). More on
this distinction in another article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before a company can improve its innovation capabilities, it's a good
idea to understand how innovative it is right now. Here's a little
table that can be used as inspiration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Risk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How are we managing risk - is there a process to mature new
ideas or are we hoping for success by doing research while we
are developing the product?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;aside class="topic"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title"&gt;Focus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are we assuming innovation is something everyone is supposed to do
or is there a more formal innovation process or team?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;aside class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: ERROR/3 (&lt;span class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;, line 53)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content block expected for the "topic" directive; none found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;.. topic:: Profile
    Are we rotating people into innovation projects based only on their
    skills or are we also ensuring they have an innovation mindset?
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest sources of failure for companies that want to be
innovative is to ignore the difference between research and development.
Innovation is not about taking risks and hoping for a good outcome - it's
about evaluating and being realistic about risks and rewards as you learn
more about your product and its market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting a focused team on innovation might seem like a bad idea - after all
who doesn't want to be innovative? If innovation is one of your KPIs or OKRs
across multiple functions, it can set your teams up for intense competition
for budget, people, and recognition. That's why it's a good idea to rotate
people into an innovation team beased on their profile and also their interest in
the problem being researched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often hear leaders talk about the Apollo program (they usually mean all
the programs leading up to putting a human on the moon). You will often
hear about "moonshot" programs, or "reach for the stars and you will get to
the moon". The Apollo program was not built on hopes and dreams. It was
accomplished with the help of great leadership, separating financial from
technical decisions, building risky components in parallel using different
technologies to minimize dependencies, and instilling a sense of a common
goal with joint responsibility for the very clear outcome of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apollo program was an extremely expensive way to get things done and
is a perfect example of the iron triangle of project management. Delivering
a high quality product in a very short time will cost a lot of money. The
program also had its share of failure and disappointment along the way, but
it also had at its core a shared vision and motivated, dedicated staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="innovation-is-steady-progress"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Innovation Is Steady Progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img alt="GE Kitchn Hub Microwave" class="align-right" src="https://fixitinfirmware.com/images/products/ge_kitchen_hub_microwave.thumbnail.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innovation can be risky, it's just common business sense to not put all
your eggs in one basket. This story might make the point clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say your business is consumer goods, specifically cooking appliances
like residential stoves. For years families cooked on two main types of
heat - gas or electric. Gas burners have not changed much over the years. They
are hard to keep clean and waste a lot of energy by allowing the heat of
the flame to escape around the side of the pot. Chefs love gas because they
can quickly change the heat reaching the food by adjusting the flame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric burners have not changed very much either. They are electric coils that
basically heat up your pot from underneath. The knobs on the stove
regulate the temperature by turning the supply of electricity fully on and off
as needed to maintain a temperature. The coils are easy to remove and replace
but hard to clean and require an opening in the stove top which can make spills
really messy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a while solid electric elements were popular because they looked easy to clean
but they had so much thermal mass that it was almost impossible to control the
heat quickly - plus they looked ugly and stayed hot for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://schott-ceran.com"&gt;Schott Ceran&lt;/a&gt; - a miracle material that allows extreme heat under
the glass, and magically keeps most of the heat from spreading to the entire
surface. It's also very strong and durable and is easy to clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so good. The other half of this story is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Induction_heating"&gt;induction heating&lt;/a&gt; which has
been around since Michael Faraday's time. The first patents for induction cooking
were issued around 1909, and Frigidaire had a practical demonstration stove
as early as the 1950's. Westinghouse produced the "Cool Top 2" induction stove
for about 2 years in the 1970's, and it cost about USD 8,260 in 2017 dollars!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Induction_cooking"&gt;induction cooking&lt;/a&gt; has a number of really big advantages including
a one-piece spill-proof top, easy cleanup if something does spill or boil over,
amazingly low heat transfer through the glass material, and high energy
efficiency. The disavantage is that it really only works well with steel,
iron, and some types of stainless steel pots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with innovation? Both technologies had been
around for a long time but induction remained a very expensive option
that only a few could afford. As late as 2012 less than 5% of homes in
the US had an induction cooktop, but the number is changing rapidly - the
acceptance has hit an inflection point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The innovation was a combination of detailed market analysis, relentless
cost reduction, experimenting with manufacturing processes, and modern touch
sensitive controls that further reduced the visual complexity of the cooktop.
It used very powerful word-of-mouth endorsements as fuel for the marketing
engine, and appealed to families that were trying to take advantage of
a more streamlined look in their new or renovated kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the point of the story - no appliance manufacturer decided to be super
"innovative" and bet the farm on induction cook tops. That's gambling. Instead
a few industry leaders that had effective research and development areas
built a limited number of units for sale knowing that they had to educate
users and appliance service people, knowing that they would most likely accept
lower (hopefully not negative) net revenue, and knowing that going all in
and putting too many early production cooktops in homes could lead to a
PR nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innovation in a company that has a well-understood business model and product
assortment respects that existing sales fund the research and development
needed to drive innovation. These companies continue to innovate
on the existing products in terms of features, cost reduction of components,
improving reliability, and simplifying the production and serviceability of
their products. They continue to market innovations on existing products by
doing experiments on financing, service agreements, providing incentive
programs to their sales channels, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the Westinghouse Cool Top 2? It was only produced for 2 years in the 70's.
It was expensive and ahead of its time. Westinghouse continued to sell their
conventional appliances because they knew that they could not bet the business
on an appliance that only a few people could ever afford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But eventually market conditions changed, some of the electronic components
became more cost effective, and eventually there were enough induction cooktops
in the maret to hit a point where they were not unusual or exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, don't ignore your core business when striving to be
innovative. Respect your existing product line and remember that innovation
comes after your research department has matured an idea to the point
where your development teams can muture the idea into a new or existing
product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>development</category><category>innovation</category><category>management</category><category>research</category><guid>https://fixitinfirmware.com/posts/lets-be-innovative/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coding Standards Are A Waste Of Time </title><link>https://fixitinfirmware.com/posts/coding-standards-are-a-waste-of-time/</link><dc:creator>Ralph Hempel</dc:creator><description>&lt;img alt="MargaretHamiltonCodeStack" class="align-right" src="https://fixitinfirmware.com/images/accent/MargaretHamiltonCodeStack.thumbnail.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You've been working for hours to figure out why the system you have delivered
fails very occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have good bug reports that show it takes
about 25 days of continuous run time for the failure to occur, and it's
happened at 4 different sites now. You get a spidey sense that it might be
related to a timer and pull out your phone and fire up &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thomasokken.com/free42/"&gt;Free-42&lt;/a&gt; (because you
like RPN calculators). The math for a 1 msec timer interval says
that a 32 bit unsigned int should be good for about 50 days ... wait a
minute. The restarts happen about 25 days apart!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You find the place where someone did a calculation with the clock using
signed instead of unsigned values, and mumble "I wish that we had a coding
standard to catch this".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Said nobody. Ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you really needed was a Developer's Guide for this project, a test-driven
development mindset, and a review process that could work together with continuous
integration to have a better chance at catching the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the title is designed to catch your eye, and a coding standard is
not a bad thing. Just pick one that's already out there like the Linux Kernel
or MicroPython coding standard and call it a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="why-management-likes-coding-standards"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Management Likes Coding Standards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take a few minutes and Google "are coding standards useful" you will get
many articles and blog posts promoting the same basic benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The code will be easy to read&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The code will be easy to understand&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The code will be easy to maintain&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The code will be easy to debug&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is exactly the kind of fluff that management likes to read after yet
another difficult project delivery. Sometimes consultants are brought in to
review the development process and they comment on the lack of a coding standard
(among other things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If only we had a coding standard our problems would go away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, a coding standard is the easiest document to write and to have
meetings about. Everyone has an opinion about how to write pretty code, how
variables and functions should be named, and whether to use camel-case or
underlines to separate words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But is the coding standard really going to fix things? There is a hard truth in
software engineering that is often forgotten. Joel Spolsky summarized it very
neatly in Part 1 of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/04/06/things-you-should-never-do-part-i/"&gt;Things You Should Never Do&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a subtle reason that programmers always want to throw away the code
and start over. The reason is that they think the old code is a mess. And
here is the interesting observation: they are probably wrong. The reason that
they think the old code is a mess is because of a cardinal, fundamental law of
programming:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s harder to read code than to write it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why code reuse is so hard. This is why everybody on your team has a
different function they like to use for splitting strings into arrays of
strings. They write their own function because it’s easier and more fun than
figuring out how the old function works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Joel Spolsky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's explore these magic bullet points a bit further and I'll try to convince
you to minimize the effort on picking a coding standard and focus instead on
making a Developer's Guide that will help the team on your next project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="but-coding-standards-make-reading-code-easier"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But Coding Standards Make Reading Code Easier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; actually a little easier to read well-formed code, but
that's something you can fix in a few minutes with any number of code
formatting utilities. You can fix up most naming problems with a decent editor
and a few miunutes of extra time to choose (or change to) a meanginful name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can't make a complex module easier to understand, maintain, or
debug just by having a coding standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels good to write and read a nicely formatted block of code where the
names all make sense, the flow is clear, and the comments explain the thinking
behind the hard parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now multiply that by a few hundred files and pretty soon you are in the 20-50
kloc range - here's where the time you and your team discussed the number of
spaces to indent a block or enforcing only one exit point per function was
wasted. You would have been better off working on a project level design and
a Developers Guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="but-coding-standards-make-understanding-code-easier"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But Coding Standards Make Understanding Code Easier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure. For projects with a hundred or so lines of code. Do you really think that
your coding standard is the one thing that is keeping new team members from
understanding how your interrupt domain functions buffer data so the background
task can process it when it's needed? Or how you guarantee that time critical
hardware updates can run during garbage collection cycles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter if the code is easy to read if the system is hard to
understand. That's why there are &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.cliffsnotes.com/"&gt;Cliff's Notes&lt;/a&gt; for topics like The Great Gatsby
and Differential Equations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's very helpful to have a relatively short document to give you and your team
a detailed guide to the technical challenges the system is designed to solve as
well as a Developer's Guide that explains how those challenges are solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait. Isn't writing a Design Guide and Developer's Guide exactly what we
are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; supposed to do anymore? Doesn't Agile prefer working code over
documentation? Shouldn't we avoid doing Big Up Front Design (BUFD)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe, yes, and yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm no fan of BUFD - unless it's for a relatively small
piece of code where you know all the design constraints and requirements and
you have good acceptance criteria and your team has written some variant of
this code more than once or twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any complex project that's going to run for a few quarters or years there
is no way to think ahead to all the problems or to find a process to eliminate
risk. And that's why you and your team should spend your time writing Design
Guides and Developer's Guides as you go. Take time in each sprint to update
these guides with new knowledge for the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For long-running and complex projects, your biggest enemy is not the lack of
coding standards. It's staff turnover and adding more developers to the
project. The loss of tribal knowledge and the friction of onboarding new
developers is what's going to be the root cause of many issues that can be
avoided if you spend time writing great guides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="but-coding-standards-make-maintanance-and-debugging-easier"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But Coding Standards Make Maintanance and Debugging Easier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A coding standard might make the &lt;em&gt;mechanics&lt;/em&gt; of maintaining code easier, but
they sure don't help you find &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; to make the changes to add features or
fix bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debugging code is one of the hardest activities there is, and a coding standard
is not going to help with that either. There are of course a few general rules
that can be used to make it easier for the compiler to tell you about a
potential bug. And there are static and dynamic code analyzers that can point
you to dangerous constructs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, this is completely backwards. For full disclosure I was a
strong advocate for compile time and code analyzers to find potential bugs. I
changed my mind when I discovered Test-Driven Development (TDD).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually I discovered the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.amazon.com/Driven-Development-Embedded-Pragmatic-Programmers/dp/193435662X"&gt;TDD For Embedded Systems&lt;/a&gt; book by James Grenning back
in 2011, but I didn't really dig in and &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; TDD until I refactored my
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rhempel/umm_malloc"&gt;umm_malloc&lt;/a&gt; project using TDD in about 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I wrote a non-trivial (2000 loc) feature extension for another project
using TDD. It worked pretty much the first time it was integrated it into the
codebase running on our embedded target.  When I reflected on how TDD improved
our development process I realized that &lt;em&gt;I never had to use the debugger&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever. Not even once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, the bit about debugging being easier when you have a coding
standard is simply untrue. Easier maintenance is also a myth - you still have
to know where to change the code, or how to plug a new feature in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="what-can-we-do-to-improve-outcomes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What Can We Do To Improve Outcomes?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing we can do is take a look around us and have some hard
conversations about &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we think a coding standard is so important, and
if so, does it need to apply uniformly to each and every project?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to argue that a coding standard is not nearly as important as a project level
Developers Guide - unless your department only works on variants of the same
codebase for all projects. I'll also ask you to recall all the hours you have
spent getting to a semi-done coding standard, giving up in the end because
you cannot get an agreement on something like allowing an early return out
of a function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we can do a literature survey looking for actual (not anecdotal)
evidence of the benefit of a coding standard - even an industry standard one
like MISRA-C. Guess what? A &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://resolver.tudelft.nl/uuid:646de5ba-eee8-4ec8-8bbc-2c188e1847ea"&gt;study at TU Delft&lt;/a&gt; (a very well respected CS school)
and Les Hatton's paper on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.leshatton.org/Documents/MISRA_comp_1105.pdf"&gt;Language Subsetting&lt;/a&gt; using MISRA-C have shown that
the standard is not much better than random chance at catching faults. To make
matters worse, Hatton's earlier paper shows that there is a non-trivial chance
that fixing code to be MISRA-C compliant actually &lt;em&gt;increases&lt;/em&gt; the risk of
introducing new and subtle bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third thing you and your team can do is start working in pairs or small
groups to break down your functional components into pieces that are
decoupled from the rest of the system, and that follow good software engineering
principles, like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://blog.cleancoder.com/uncle-bob/2020/10/18/Solid-Relevance.html"&gt;Uncle Bob's SOLID&lt;/a&gt; response to a reader's letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, find a TDD evangelist in your team and take them off their
assigned tasks for a while. Let them float in a couple of teams and ask them
to coach developers in TDD. Make sure that your developers know the difference
between code &lt;em&gt;coverage&lt;/em&gt; and code &lt;em&gt;correctness&lt;/em&gt; - it's usually easy to write
tests after the code is done that prove code coverage. That doesn't mean its
correct - and I've been bitten by that more than once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes a little longer (at the beginning) to write code that makes failing tests
pass, but pretty soon the rhythm of writing a test, breaking your program, and then
writing code to make the test pass becomes natural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your new developers will be &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more productive on your complex system
if they have read a good Developers Guide and understand the workflow for
adding features or fixing (hopefully rare) bugs. They won't need a Coding
Standard because you'll have a senior staff member coaching them for the
first few months, they will have a safety net of tests, and they will develop
a mindset that drives quality, attention to detail, and testability that a
coding standard simply cannot help with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to press for Design and Developer's Guides for your projects, and
to focus on becoming great at TDD and using your CI pipeline to run tests
automatically. Learn to build decoupled systems and to work in pairs or close
knit groups to keep each other thinking about how to write great code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result should be an awesome project. Nobody will care about which
Coding Standard you used ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>code</category><category>maintenance</category><guid>https://fixitinfirmware.com/posts/coding-standards-are-a-waste-of-time/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>