<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Fix It In Firmware (Posts about teams)</title><link>https://fixitinfirmware.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://fixitinfirmware.com/categories/teams.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:rhempel@fixitinfirmware.com"&gt;Ralph Hempel&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 02:04:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Don't Scale Your Successful Teams</title><link>https://fixitinfirmware.com/posts/dont-scale-your-teams/</link><dc:creator>Ralph Hempel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fixitinfirmware.com/images/accent/WoolSheep.jpg" class="image-reference" title="foo"&gt;&lt;img src="https://fixitinfirmware.com/images/accent/WoolSheep.jpg" alt="Woolen sheep of various sizes in a wooden box with dividers" title="Wool Sheeep" class=" align-right"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team you have been a part of for the last 6 months has been amazing. No, they
haven't pulled a month of 60+ hour work weeks to get a new release out the
door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has just been a stream of steady progress towards a shared goal, true collaboration
instead of procedural coordination, willingness to change ways of working
in small steps, and a sense of getting really good at what they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team is getting noticed, not for heroics, but for simply getting sh#t done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that recognition comes the request to somehow capture the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; that your
team is using, and then replicate or scale that to other teams. What could possibly
go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just about everything - starting with the assumption that the high-functioning team is
somehow adhering to a checklist of process steps to efficiently deliver value, and by
extension good outcomes for the business. Similarly, high-functioning teams in an
organization that doesn't support collaboaration are doomed to an existence of
frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's almost impossible to "process" your way out of trouble when doing complex work, but
you can definitely make your culture more friendly to complex work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive a little deeper, and hopefully come away with an appreciation of how a
high-functioning team gets that way, and why scaling that team's ways of working
rarely has the intended impact across the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fixitinfirmware.com/posts/dont-scale-your-teams/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (8 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>codereview</category><category>teams</category><guid>https://fixitinfirmware.com/posts/dont-scale-your-teams/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>